Finding Aid for Thankful O. Jones Papers, 1835-1914
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Thankful O. Jones Papers 1835-1914 1861-1865
Jones, Thankful O. (Thankful Olivia), 1814-1894.
0.3 linear ft.
Papers of Thankful O. Jones and other members of the Jones and Burch families of New York state and Clinton County, Michigan. Civil War papers of son Harlem, soldier with Co. K, 11th New York Volunteer Cavalry; letters of other family members concerning daily activities, business and fraternal affairs, and life in Maple Rapids, Michigan, in the 1890s; also photographs.
85239 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Virginia Allan (donor no. 5667 ), May 17, 1984.
The collection is open for research.
Thankful Olivia Burch was born October 18, 1814, one of twelve children born to Abigail Rose and Asa Burch II. In 1841 she married William Jones of Venice. Together, they had eight children: sons Harlem, Morgan, James Eli, Asa, and Orland, and daughters Emily, Mary, and Hattie. She also raised a step-son, Amos S. Jones, from her husband's previous marriage.
Upon the death of their father in 1861, Harlem, Morgan, Eli, and Amos enlisted in the Union Army. Both Harlem and Eli served as privates in Company K of the 11th New York Volunteer Cavalry. Stationed first on Staten Island, they were transferred to Washington, DC in 1862, where they saw action at Bull Run and other skirmishes in northern Virginia. The following year the two brothers marched with their Company to Louisiana, where they participated in the Union assault on Baton Rouge. Harlem, who corresponded frequently with his mother and sisters died of an illness in a military hospital at New Orleans on December 25, 1864. His brother Eli returned home in 1865.
The careers of Morgan and Amos are less fully documented in this collection. Morgan was killed in action in March of 1864, but his company is not recorded. Amos served in Company E of the 9th New York Artillery and was stationed at the headquarters of General George Meade at Petersburg, Virginia.
At the conclusion of the war Thankful O. Jones resided with her son Eli, following the latter's marriage to Helen Perrigo. In 1867 the family moved to St. Johns, Clinton County, Michigan after a brief residence in Calhoun County. During the 1870s she maintained correspondence with her brother Varnum D. Burch of Jefferson City, Missouri and Godfrey, Madison County, Illinois, and numerous Burch family nieces and nephews.
In 1892, Thankful Jones moved to Durand, Shiawassee County with her son Eli, but returned to Clinton County the following year to reside near her son Asa at Maple Rapids. She was an active supporter of the Woman's Relief Corps of Maple Rapids where she was affectionately called "Grandma Jones." She died at Maple Rapids on December 20, 1894.
The papers of Thankful O. Jones reflect the private interests and concerns of a nineteenth century woman and members of her family who lived variously in New York, Missouri, Illinois, and Michigan. The collection includes correspondence sent to Thankful Jones from her siblings and children, but does not contain any of her own writings.
The bulk of the letters was written by Harlem B. Jones during his service in the Civil War. Writing to his mother and sister Emily on a weekly or semi-weekly basis, Harlem describes in detail his unfavorable impressions of camp life; his observations on the military strategies of Stonewall Jackson, Joe Hooker, and Ambrose Burnside; and his participation in the battle of Bull Run and the assault on Baton Rouge. Harlem also relates briefly his impression of Washington, DC, Abraham Lincoln, and the Presidential Election of 1864.
Also included are Civil War letters from Thankful Jones's step-son, Amos S. Jones, and from her nephew, Nelson C. Burch. These letters pertain largely to family news and interests.
Thankful Jones also maintained extensive correspondence with her brother Varnum D. Burch of Madison County, Illinois and Jefferson City, Missouri, following the Civil War. These letters reflect a variety of topics, ranging from health and living conditions to the anguish caused by a sexual indiscretion and the subsequent relations with an illegitimate child. Other correspondents of the Burch family include Sabina Burch and Lucy R. (Burch) Jones, sisters of Thankful; nephews Nelson C. Burch of Jefferson City and John C. Burch of Crawfordsville, Indiana; niece Celestia A. Moore, Abbie R. Flagg, and Hattie Willard; and F. A. Willett, a brother-in-law. Several letters from Thankful's son Asa reflect his life in Maple Rapids, Michigan in the 1890s; and those of Libbie Anderson document Thankful Jones' interest in the Woman's Relief Corps of Maple Rapids.
The collection also contains numerous military documents reflecting the Civil War service of Harlem and J. Eli Jones, as well as numerous deeds and estate papers of William Jones. Thankful Jones's efforts to settle her husband's estate and to secure the pension of her son Harlem are reflected in her business and military service correspondence. The papers also contain some Jones family biographical and genealogical material.
The collection also includes some papers of the Matthews-Owen family of Pittsford, New York and Owosso, Shiawassee County, Michigan. Included are some military papers of Henry Matthews and several letters to Mary Ann Matthews from her sister Abigail L. Ely and cousin Julia Owen, dating from 1835 to 1841. The relationship of this family with that of Thankful O. Jones remains unclear, but the papers do reflect conditions in Penfield and Fairport, New York in the 1830s and 1840s. Among the letters is an account of a duel in Washington, DC in 1838.
Subjects:
Burch family.; Clinton County (Mich.).; Jones family.; Jones, Thankful O. (Thankful Olivia), 1814-1894.; Maple Rapids (Mich.).; Michigan--Social life and customs--1891-1900.; New York (State)--Social life and customs.; United States. Army. New York Cavalry Regiment, 11th (1861-1865). Company K.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Women--Michigan--Clinton County.; Michigan--Social life and customs--19th century.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Jones, Thankful O. (Thankful Olivia), 1814-1894.; Women.
Contributors:
Jones, Harlem.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Thankful O. Jones
  - Civil War correspondence
    - Harlem Jones, 1861-1862 (Box 1)
    - Harlem and Amos Jones, 1863-1865 (Box 1)
  - Burch and Related family correspondence, 1868-1899 (Box 1)
  - Business correspondence, 1868-1892 (Box 1)
  - Photograph portrait (Box 1)
- Jones Family
  - Harlem B. Jones
    - Military Documents and Related Correspondence, 1864-1878 (Box 1)
  - James Eli Jones
    - Military and Fraternal Lodge Documents, 1865-1914 (Box 1)
  - Jones family
    - Obituaries and Genealogical Material (Box 1)
  - Jones and Burch family
    - Deeds and Estates, 1858-1896 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Business Papers and Personal Notes, 1867-1889 (Box 1)
- Matthews-Owen family (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1835-1841